It's hot!
真熱！
Huh? Huh? Why?
咦？怎麼了？
What! A flat tire.
什麼啊！洩氣了
Not when it's so hot out.
不是吧？在天氣那麼熱的時候
Whoa, it's heavier than I thought.
哇，比我想像中還要重
-Let's go! -Magical universe!
-開始！ -神奇宇宙！
You say universe, I say Milky Way.
你說宇宙，我說銀河
You say Milky Way, I say celestial.
你說銀河，我說天空
You say celestial, I say Earth.
妳說天空，我說地球
-Good morning, Kosugi. -Good morning.
-小杉，早安 -早安
Wow, look at that textbook.
那教科書真厲害
Won't you join the Special--
小杉，妳要不要參加專…
I have to go.
失陪了
-Good morning. -Morning!
-大家早安 -早
Ma'am, we didn't understand something, so we were discussing it.
對了，老師 我們有些地方不懂，剛剛正在討論呢
I don't get this part about "mean" from yesterday.
昨天教的“mean”我不太懂
-Oh this. -Is it "mean" like "meaning"…
-這個啊 -是不是“意義”的意思？
You want to join!
你果然想加入嗎？
That's ridiculous.
開什麼玩笑？
-Of course I don't. -You seem very interested.
-我當然不想了 -你看起來很感興趣
I just came to see what the dummies were up to.
我只是來看看這些笨蛋在幹嘛
That's called being interested.
那不就是感興趣的意思？
Hey, Fujii, that bet we had.
喂，藤井，我們之前打的賭
Joining the camp if you lost. You remember you promised to come.
要是你輸了就加入專科，你答應過的
You are welcome anytime to join the course.
隨時歡迎你加入專科
But carry your chair and desk here yourself.
但你得自己把桌子和椅子搬過來
Study camp?
合宿？
The Special Course will have a three-day study camp.
東大專科將要辦一場三天的合宿
I came to get your permission for them.
我代他們來取得理事長的同意
They can do what they want.
他們愛怎麼做就怎麼做
Also, it seems that the UTokyo Special Course
另外，看來東大專科
may be close to welcoming Fujii and Kosugi.
或許會迎來藤井和小杉的加入
We can't allow that!
我們絕不能允許！
If that's what they want to do, we can watch quietly.
如果他們願意，我們也只能靜靜旁觀
But if they join, they'll definitely get into UTokyo.
但是理事長 要是他們加入，他們一定能考上東大
The chances of you having to quit will get higher.
妳得退出的機率就會變高
About that. The former chairman said he wants me to be chairman.
關於那件事 前任理事長說他想讓我當理事長
All I can think about now is rebuilding the school.
我現在只一心想著重建學校
And honestly, becoming the chairman is…
老實說，要當理事長…
I know you're happy, don't try to hide it.
我知道你很高興，不用隱藏了
Huh?
什麼？
Pardon me.
失陪了
He's such a nasty man! Despite being vice principal.
教務主任真是不改卑鄙的作風
Okuda, did you find out who the former chairman was talking to?
奧田，你查出前理事長 和誰來往了嗎？
He seems to be in the real estate business.
是，他看來是經營房地產的
-Perhaps home renovations? -You know it's about selling the school.
-或許是家裡要裝修？ -你知道他要賣掉學校吧！
What?! Was he still looking into that?
什麼？他還沒放棄那件事嗎？
So that's it.
原來如此
He was using the vice principal to get me to step down.
他利用教務主任讓我退出
So he could sell the school.
好讓他把學校賣掉
-"Run, Melos"? -We read this in junior high.
-《跑吧！美樂斯》？ -我們國中的時候讀過了
It's about a guy who runs for his friend, right?
這是一個男人為了朋友 而不斷奔跑的故事，對吧？
What are we supposed to do?
我們要做什麼？
You have 10 minutes to sum it up in 100 words.
現在開始，你們有十分鐘 用不超過一百字總結這故事
-100 words in 10 minutes? -Sum it up? How?
-十分鐘內一百字？ -總結？怎麼做？
Oh yeah, Mizuno. You too.
對了，水野，妳也要
Uh, me?
我也要？
Okay, we're starting.
好，我們開始啦
Ready, start!
準備，開始！
"Melos was enraged." What a first line.
“美樂斯被激怒了” 第一句就那麼厲害
Was Melos angry because the king kept killing people?
美樂斯會生氣 是因為國王一直濫殺無辜嗎？
Melos had a little sister who was about to be married.
美樂斯有位即將結婚的妹妹
He wanted to go to the wedding
他想出席婚禮
so his friend Selinuntius became a hostage.
所以他的朋友塞里努丟斯成為了人質
He ran until he was exhausted. That's cool.
他一直跑到筋疲力竭為止 真是了不起
Melos made it on time! Good.
美樂斯趕到了，太好了！
Okay, stop! Hey.
好，停！來
Give it. Sheesh.
給我，嘖
Huh?
什麼？
Stop!
別寫了
Hey, c'mon!
喂，給我！
-Stop! -Ugh, damn it.
-別寫了！ -啊，可惡
These are terrible.
真糟糕啊
Kenta, you wrote "Melon" instead of "Melos."
健太，你把“美樂斯” 寫成“香瓜”了
Oh, huh?
咦？是嗎？
-Kenta… -Keep laughing, Amano.
-健太… -繼續笑吧，天野
Yours is completely off-target.
你的完全離題了
Huh?
什麼？
Hayase, I'm not asking for your opinion.
早瀨，我沒問妳的意見
Summarize the story in 100 words.
我要妳在一百字內總結這故事
And Seto.
還有瀨戶
Your handwriting is so bad, I can't read it.
你字寫得太難看了，我看不懂
Mizuno.
水野
Excellent as always.
一如既往的好
Of the students, Iwazaki did the best.
學生當中，岩崎做得最好
Nice! But to summarize,
太好了！但要總結
I didn't know what to write or leave out.
我不知道該寫什麼，該捨棄什麼
Do you know why?
妳知道為什麼嗎？
Why?
為什麼？
It's because you have poor reading comprehension.
那是因為你們毫無閱讀理解能力
You keep using words that I don't know!
你老是用那些我不明白的詞！
Reading comprehension is about what the writer wants to say.
閱讀理解和作者想表達什麼有關
That is to say, the ability to summarize concisely.
也就是說，簡明扼要的總結能力
Your reading comprehension is definitely lacking.
你們的閱讀理解能力絕對不足
I can tell you've never touched a book in your life.
我看得出你們人生中 連一本書都沒有碰過吧
I've read a lot of illustrated reference books.
我讀了很多有插圖的參考書
Sorry, your writing was so bad I didn't feel like reading it.
不好意思，你的字體太難看了 我連讀都不想讀
Oh, is that all? Hey!
什麼啊？喂！
Reading comprehension is linked to how much you read as a child.
閱讀理解和你們童年的閱讀量有關
Reading with a parent or on your own. Looking up information.
和父母一起或是獨自閱讀，查閱資料
Those with those habits as children have reading comprehension.
在兒童階段就有這能力的人 就會有閱讀理解能力
As children? Isn't it too late now?
兒童階段？那不是太遲了嗎？
Yeah, there's less than a year until the exam.
是啊，距離考試只有不到一年
It's not too late. There's a training method you can use.
不會太遲，有種訓練方式適合你們
Oh! Tell us sooner!
什麼啦，快告訴我們嘛！
What sort of training?
哪種訓練？
Tomorrow at 6 a.m., be in uniform at the Dragon Zakura with overnight gear.
明早六點，在龍櫻前 穿好制服，帶著過夜的裝備
Tomorrow?!
明天？
Tell us sooner!
早點說啊！
Not a study camp from hell?
該不會是地獄集訓合宿？
-Exactly right. -Whoa.
-沒錯 -啊
-Hey, hey! -Huh?
-喂！ -嗯？
-No, uh… -I invited a special instructor.
-沒事，那個… -我請來了一位特別講師
-Again? -The Spartan instructor?
-又來嗎？ -斯巴達講師嗎？
This one is even scarier.
這次的更可怕
Seriously?
不是吧？
You're kidding.
你在開玩笑吧？
We're finally starting the study camp.
我們終於要開始合宿了
I've already made a three-day curriculum so we can start anytime.
我已經提前排好三天的課表 所以隨時可以開始
-Oh, have you? -Yes.
-哦，是嗎？ -是
Kosugi, our study camp starts tomorrow. You come too.
小杉，我們的合宿明天開始 妳也來吧
Sir, Kosugi won't be able to.
老師，小杉沒辦法加入
-I'll think about it. -Okay.
-我會考慮 -好
Huh?
什麼？
That means there's a possibility, right?
那代表有機會，對吧？
Yeah.
嗯
STUDY CAMP DAY 1
（早上六點，合宿第一天）
Whew! I'm sleepy!
我好睏
This is too early.
這也太早了
Huh? Amano.
咦？天野
-I'm no good at early mornings. -Hey.
-我不擅長太早起 -喂
Whoa! Hey!
喂！
-I like mornings. -Are you a rooster?
-我喜歡早晨 -你是公雞嗎？
A study camp! This is real test prep now, how exciting!
合宿什麼的 我們好像真正的考生了，好興奮呀
-Don't quit like always. -That's definitely not happening.
-別像平時一樣退出 -這絕對不會發生
Kosugi.
小杉
I'm here to help Kenta.
我是來陪健太的
Looking forward to it!
請多指教囉
Yeah…
嗯…
Hey guys, welcome.
喂，你們都來啦
Racewalk 20 times around the Dragon Zakura.
你們先繞著龍櫻競走20圈
Get your brain in gear, then come up.
讓大腦動起來，然後上來
Iwazaki, you can walk.
岩崎，妳可以用走的
-Huh? -I'm sleepy…
-什麼？ -我好想睡覺…
Kenta, too fast.
健太，你太快了
Yeah!
好！
No slacking!
別拖拖拉拉！
I said racewalking!
我說競走！
-Oh man. -Walk properly!
-糟了 -給我好好走！
Twenty laps first thing in the morning is too much.
大清早第一件事 就要走20圈也太多了
-Seto, you cheated. -Did not!
-瀨戶，你耍賴 -才沒有！
-You did.
-你有
But Amano was slow too.
但天野也很慢
I'm just naturally slow!
我本來就走得慢
-Why are you here? -Fair's fair.
-你怎麼也在？ -輸了就是輸了
-I promised, so I came. -Huh?
-我答應過，所以我來了 -什麼？
-I can't believe you came. -Did you hit your head?
-沒想到你真的會來 -藤井，你敲到頭了嗎？
-Huh? -Do you want to join the course?
-什麼？ -原來你想參加專科啊？
Of course I don't.
當然不想了
I can't believe this.
真是無法相信
What a racket. So what if Fujii came? Good for him.
吵死了，藤井來又怎麼樣？ 對他來說很好啊
-You were there? -Stop staring.
-你一直在那裡？ -別看了
Put away your bags and sit down.
放下你們的行李，坐下來
No matter the time you have, it's not enough.
你們有多少時間都不夠用
Learn from them.
和他們學學吧
Sheesh.
真是
Good morning.
早安
Finally the study camp. Mizuno, I'm counting on you.
終於辦合宿了，水野，拜託妳了
Mr. Takahara. Thank you.
高原老師，謝謝
You got permission from the chairman.
多虧你獲得了理事長的同意
It's all I could do to help everyone.
不會，我只能這樣幫助大家了
-Do your best! -Yes, sir.
-加油！ -是
Mr. Sakuragi. Thanks in advance.
櫻木老師，麻煩你了
-Bye. -Alright, we're starting.
-先走了 -好，我們要開始了
Your schedule for today is…
你們今天的行程表是…
This.
這個
Today, you are free.
你們今天自由活動
-Free? -Huh?
-自由？ -什麼？
What are you saying? Follow the schedule!
等一下，你說什麼？ 照著原本的行程表走啊！
Use your time freely. Do whatever you want.
自由地使用你們的時間 想做什麼就做什麼
If it's free study, what's the point?
等一下，如果只是自習 合宿不就沒意義了？
I came all the way here. That's not cool.
我還特地來這裡，真是沒意思
Are you leaving?
你要走了嗎？
I'm pretty sure you lost the bet…
但我記得你打賭輸了…
There! Okay, get to it.
那就對了！好，開始吧
-Hey, wait! -Hang on, sir!
-喂，別走！ -等一下，老師！
Huh?
什麼？
For now, study!
現在先自習吧！
-Isn't that irresponsible? -Seriously!
-真的好不負責任 -對啊
Independent study?
自習？
Alright!
好！
Sir, what do you mean they're free to do whatever all day?
老師，你說他們今天一整天 自由活動是什麼意思？
I assembled a tight three-day menu!
我可是設計了緊湊的三天菜單！
-Menu? -A 16-hour study schedule, like we did.
-菜單？ -像我們以前的16小時學習計畫
To give them the endurance to study.
訓練他們的學習耐力
-What era are you living in? -Huh?!
-妳是哪個年代的人啊？ -什麼？
Your success story makes this harder.
妳的成功經驗有時反而是絆腳石
Old-fashioned education methods become garbage over time.
隨著年代轉變 老套的教育方式已經變成垃圾了
-Garbage? -Coercion and obedience are over.
-垃圾？ -強迫和服從的年代已經結束了
-Huh? -Those guys have modern values.
-什麼？ -這些人有現代的價值觀
First, we have to recognize that. Then trust them.
我們首先要認識到這一點 然後信任他們
The role of the adult is those two things.
成人的角色就是這兩件事
But what about the special literature instructor?
但老師，語文特別講師那裡怎麼辦？
Didn't you say you invited him?
你不是說你邀請了他嗎？
Sheesh.
真是
It's no good. I can't focus!
沒辦法，我無法專注！
Hey, Kosugi. How can I focus for hours on end and study like you?
嘿，小杉，我要怎麼做 才能像妳一樣專注幾小時念書？
I wanna know too!
我也想知道
I want to know why you guys can't do it.
我倒是想知道為什麼妳們做不到
Right…
這樣說也是…
-Where are you going? -To the bathroom.
-妳要去哪？ -去廁所
Hang on!
等一下
I'm going to learn words outside.
我也要出去學單字
Me too!
我也要
Huh? Hang on!
什麼？等一下
Seriously!
真是！
Recognize their values and trust them? But I am worried.
認識他們的價值觀並信任他們？ 但我果然放不下心
Huh? Where is everyone else?
咦？其他人呢？
They left.
他們走了
-I guess they ran away. -No!
-他們應該是逃走了吧 -不是吧？
Ah, damn it!
啊，可惡！
Seto.
瀨戶
I wanted to stretch a bit.
我也想出來活動一下身體
I can't do this. Studying and stuff.
果然我不是念書的料
I thought I'd catch up, but I can't.
我以為我能跟上，但我沒辦法
Hey, about studying.
我說啊，在念書上
Those who can, and those who can't.
那些做得到的人和做不到的人
What's different?
他們有什麼差別？
"I am a good fisherman."
“我是個好漁夫”
Amano! Amano!
天野！
Were you sleeping?
你不會睡著了吧？
No, I was watching Study Sapuri, and I just, uh…
不是，我剛剛在看學習補品 然後我就…
It was just a second. I swear.
但只是一瞬間而已，我發誓
I just did a lap around the school.
我還繞了學校一圈呢
Do you want to go back?
要不要回去了？
Yeah.
好啊
Kosugi's textbooks are so worn out.
小杉的課本真破舊
How many times could she have read them?
她到底翻了多少次才讓書變這樣？
Those guys are amazing.
那些人真了不起
I don't want to lose to them.
我不想輸給他們
Me neither.
我也不想
Where did they all go?
他們都去了哪裡？
-You guys get ready. -Okay!
-你們準備好了！ -好！
Mr. Sakuragi, what are you doing?!
櫻木老師，你在幹嘛？
-Oof! -Okay!
-呼！ -哎呀！
-Sir, do we carry all this? -Yeah, thanks.
-老師，這些全都要搬下來嗎？ -對，謝謝
-Okay! Got it! -Hey! Hello!
-好！沒問題！ -嘿！妳好
Hey, Mizuno. What are you doing?
水野，妳在幹嘛？
Oh yeah. It's terrible! Everyone left.
對了，糟糕了，大家都走了
They're in the classroom.
他們在教室裡
Huh?
什麼？
Why?
為什麼？
That means they're not as dumb as you think.
這代表他們沒有妳想像的笨
Huh?
什麼？
The UTokyo exam isn't easy.
東大入學考不容易
They have to win out over thousands of brilliant students.
他們得要打敗成千上萬的優秀學生
If your competitive spirit doesn't burn bright, you won't win.
競爭意識沒被燃起的人是不會贏的
They may have realized this.
他們可能意識到這件事了
Is that why you invited Fujii and Kosugi to the study camp?
這就是你邀請 藤井和小杉加入合宿的原因？
What do you think?
妳認為呢？
Let's eat!
我開動了！
Alright!
太好了！
Yum! Pork curry.
好吃！豬肉咖哩
-Delicious! -Pork is highly nutritious.
-真美味！ -豬肉的營養價值很高
It's full of vitamin B1 which helps relieve fatigue.
充滿了幫助緩解疲勞的維生素B1
Perfect for a body tired from studying.
適合你們學累了的身體
This omelet has spinach in it.
這個玉子燒裡面有菠菜
Eggs and spinach are full of the essential acids needed for brain transmitters.
雞蛋和菠菜富含腦神經遞質需要的酸
This egg dish is like a superfood for students.
這蛋料理對學生來說就像超級食物
Yummy!
好吃！
Fujii, you're eating bread? Eat with everyone!
藤井，你在吃麵包嗎？ 和大家一起吃吧
-Eat up! -Our curry is good!
-吃吧！ -我們的咖哩很美味
Here, little Fujii. Eat up.
來，小藤井，請吃
Food is important to build your brain and body.
食物對身體和大腦很重要
People who get into UTokyo value every meal.
考進東大的人會珍惜每一餐
-Yes, sir! -You guys can stop now. Thank you.
-是！ -你們可以下班了，謝謝
Oh yeah, sir. Here.
老師，這個
-Here. -What's this?
-來 -這是什麼？
"Iwai Shop"? This is an invoice!
“岩井商店”？這不是發票嗎？
Ms. Mizuno. Thanks for the dinner.
水野老師，謝謝款待
Can I have seconds?
我能再加嗎？
-Of course! Eat up and get strong. -Yes ma'am.
-當然了，吃多點對身體好 -是
Huh? Kosugi! Wow!
咦？小杉！好厲害！
Me too.
我也要
I'm full, and now I'm sleepy.
我吃飽了，現在開始想睡了
I planned on studying, but I don't think I can.
我計畫好了要念書，但我想我不行了
Because you eat fast until you're full, like idiots.
因為你們像笨蛋一樣 吃得很快，直到吃飽為止
-Huh? -Trying to maximize your study time.
-什麼？ -試著拉長學習時間
It's a typical exam prep mistake.
是典型的備考錯誤
Kosugi, what happens when people eat too fast?
小杉，人吃太快時會發生什麼事？
Their blood sugar rises quickly?
血糖快速飆升？
That's right. When blood sugar rises quickly,
沒錯，當血糖快速飆升
insulin is secreted to transform the sugar into energy.
身體會分泌胰島素，將糖轉化成能量
That's why you feel sleepy or fatigued after a meal.
這就是為什麼 吃飽飯後會覺得困倦或是疲累
Who said to eat a lot and get strong?
剛剛是誰說多吃點對身體好的？
-Oh, sorry. -Don't eat fast.
-哦，不好意思 -不要吃得太快
Don't eat until you're full.
不要吃到飽才停止
To prevent spikes in blood sugar,
為了避免血糖飆升
eat with brain energy efficiency in mind.
吃的時候要考慮能量攝取效率
Then you can focus and secure longer study hours.
這樣一來，你們就能專注 並且確保更長的學習時間
Tell us sooner!
早點說嘛！
Making the mistake helps you remember.
犯錯會讓你們記得
Alright, that's all for today.
好，今天就到此為止
Tomorrow at 6 a.m., meet in front of the Dragon Zakura
明早六點，在龍櫻前見
in uniform.
穿著制服
Six a.m. again? Isn't that too early?
又是六點？不會太早了嗎？
-Yay! -You're amazing.
-太好啦！ -你真厲害
The school is scary at night.
這學校晚上真恐怖
Ah, feels good!
啊，感覺真好！
Kosugi, you're studying at this hour?
小杉，妳這個時間還在學習嗎？
I wouldn't call this studying.
這算學習嗎？
I'm just reading it because I like it.
我讀它是因為喜歡
Wow…
真了不起…
I wonder what it's like at UTokyo?
我真好奇東大是什麼樣子
Well, I don't really know.
這個嘛，我也不知道
But if we all go together, doesn't it seem fun?
但如果我們全都一起過去 不是很有意思嗎？
Hey, you actually want to go to UTokyo, don't you?
那個，其實妳也想上東大，對吧？
Good night.
晚安
Oh, sure…
啊，好…
STUDY CAMP DAY 2
（早上5:45，合宿第二天）
Get up!
起床了！
Okay, get up!
好了，起床了！
Get up! Hey!
起床了！喂！
So loud! I was having a good dream!
真吵！我剛在做一場好夢耶
Girls too, get up!
女生們也一樣，起床！
Hey! Hey!
喂！
-I'm so sleepy. -Morning calisthenics at 6 a.m.?
-我好睏 -早上六點做健康操？
With morning calisthenics, you can limber up every part of your body.
透過健康操 活動你們身體的每個部分
It's an excellent exercise.
這是個很好的運動
And the benefits double if you do it in the morning.
而且早上做的話，帶來的好處是一倍
-Learn from Mizuno! -Yes, sir!
-和水野學學吧 -是
Why me…
為什麼是我…
…three times, hands on hips, bend backwards…
…三次，雙手放在大腿上，向後彎…
Ow, ow!
好痛！
Ma'am, you're so stiff!
老師，妳好僵硬！
People get stiff as they age, I heard.
我聽說人老了會變得僵硬
Enough from you.
你們夠了啊
If we're going to exercise first thing, why wear our uniforms?
如果起床後的第一件事是運動 為什麼要穿制服？
Yeah, gym clothes are easier to move in.
對啊，運動服更方便活動
Are you wearing gym clothes to your UTokyo exams?
你們會穿運動服去考東大入學考嗎？
Of course not.
當然不會了
This is all to make you aware of the actual exam.
這全都是為了讓你們習慣實際考試
-Huh? -Waking up at six, the same as exam day.
-什麼？ -六點起床，和考試那天一樣
Eat the same food and study during exam hours.
吃一樣的食物，在考試時間學習
Go to bed at the same time as before exam day.
和考試前一天同樣時間上床睡覺
If you always live as you would on exam day,
如果你總是像考試那天一樣生活
exam day stops being a special day.
正式考試就沒什麼特別了
Ah, I see.
原來如此
Clothing is another important way to calm yourself.
穿著也是讓自己平靜下來的重要方法
To give 100 percent on your exam,
為了能百分之百專注考試
you want the same clothes, the same routine, the same energy.
你每天得穿一樣的衣服 有一樣的生活習慣和一樣的能量
This is an important way to produce results on the day.
這是那天能夠考出好結果的重要方法
-Whoa. -Right, Fujii?
-哇 -對吧，藤井？
Exam day…
正式考試…
-When I think about it, it's scary. -Right?
-我一想到就覺得害怕 -對吧？
Then move your body!
所以動起來吧
If you don't, you'll have lost before you enter the exam building!
要是不這麼做 你們還沒進考場就已經輸了！
-Okay! -Yeah!
-好的！ -好
Shoulders! Up! Shoulders! Down!
肩膀，上！肩膀，下！
Strongly and swiftly, bend and stretch your arms.
快速而有力地彎曲和伸展你的手臂
Today I invited a special instructor.
今天我邀請了一位特別講師
A literature specialist.
一位語文專家
Mr. Osamu Dazaifu.
太宰府治老師
Osamu Dazaifu?
太宰府治？
Sir, please enter.
老師，請進
Huh?
什麼？
Mizuno.
水野
Mr. Dazaifu?
太宰府老師？
Teaching literature to prepare for the UTokyo exam?
為了準備東大入學考而教語文？
That's heavy on my heart.
這讓我的心很沉重
It's too much to bear…
太重了，我無法承受…
Huh?
咦？
I want to go home.
我想回家
Is this guy alright?
這人還好吧？
But if Mr. Sakuragi invited him…
但如果他是櫻木老師特別邀請的…
Nobody knows sentence structure.
你們沒一位瞭解句子的結構
This is trouble.
真是棘手
Literature is a science!
語文是一種科學！
All of a sudden?
這麼突然？
And creation is architecture!
而創作是建築！
A creative piece made by ignoring architecture is shit!
忽略建築的創作只是垃圾！
He suddenly changed.
他變得好快
And a superior sentence
而一個高級的句子
is one made with architectural principles!
是由建築原理組成的！
What just happened?
等一下，發生了什麼事？
Dazaifu gets passionate when he sees poor students.
太宰府老師遇到笨學生會變得很激動
But he cools off fast.
但他很快就會冷靜下來
I'm very sorry. I've calmed down.
不好意思，我冷靜下來了
Go ahead, sir.
請繼續
Listen, everyone. Sentences.
大家聽著了，句子
They all have one thing to say.
它們都有想表達的一件事
In order to convey that one thing,
為了能夠傳達這一件事
the author tries many methods, many tools.
作者會用許多方法、許多工具
Paraphrasing according to architectural principles.
根據建築原理來改述
Many methods, many tools?
許多方法、許多工具？
Yes. Reading comprehension, or summarizing,
是的，閱讀理解或是總結
is not just reading sentences.
不僅是閱讀句子而已
It's about structuring it in your head.
而是讓你在頭腦中建構它
Equivalence, contrast, cause and effect.
同等關係、對比關係、因果關係
You can structure an editorial with these three patterns.
這三種模式能用來建構一篇文章
Equivalence is the various ways
同等關係是一個句子
a sentence can be reworded.
能被改寫的各種方式
-"Equivalence"? -It sounds complicated.
-“同等關係”？ -聽起來好複雜
-How could I know what that is? -Right.
-我根本聽不懂 -是啊
Okay, please read these two sentences.
那麼，請讀這兩個句子
You can read A.
妳來念A
"I thought it would rain, but it was sunny."
“我以為會下雨，但卻放晴了
"I thought I'd get scolded,
我以為我會被責駡
but I wasn't."
但我並沒有”
You can read the B sentence.
你來念B句子
"That is to say, several unexpected lucky things happened."
“換言之，在意料之外 發生了許多好事”
These two sentences are paraphrasing the same idea
這兩個句子都在一個全新的句子內
in a new sentence. Do you understand that?
改述著同一個理念，明白了嗎？
You.
你
The expressions are different, but they're both about
表達的方式不同，但它們都和
how something unexpected happened.
對於某件事的預期有關
That's right. Taking it further,
正確，進一步說
A is concrete,
A是具體的
and B is an abstract expression.
而B是抽象的表達
Augh. I don't get it!
我不明白！
We can draw A.
我們能畫出A
Huh?
什麼？
Oh, I see!
我明白了！
Oh, so in A, it says "rain" and "sunny."
所以A句裡說了“下雨”和“放晴”
I could draw it, so it's concrete.
我能將它畫出來，所以它是具體的
-True, you couldn't draw B. -Wow!
-對耶，B是畫不出來的 -真厲害！
It looks like you are starting to get it.
看來你們開始跟上了
A equals B. A and B
A等於B，A和B之間
are connected with "that is to say."
由“換言之”聯繫著
That's the basic structure of equivalence.
這就是同等關係的基本結構
I see.
原來如此
Next is contrast. To make your point clear,
下一個是對等關係 為了清楚表達你們的觀點
indicate the opposite and compare them.
列出相反情況並比較它們
Sentences with "however" or "but."
那些含有“然而”和“但是”的句子
That's right.
沒錯
Last is cause and effect.
最後是因果關係
Could you read this for me?
妳能念這一句嗎？
"I forgot my homework, that's why I was scolded."
“我忘了作業，所以被責駡了”
This is
這是
a sentence with the cause, then effect.
先有原因，再有結果的句子
"I was scolded because I forgot my homework."
“我被責駡了，因為我忘了作業”
This is
這是
a sentence with the effect, then cause.
先有結果，再有原因的句子
I see! Cause and effect.
是這樣啊！原因和結果
I feel like I get it!
我覺得我明白了
Good.
很好
UTokyo exam questions use equivalence, comparison, and cause and effect.
東大入學考的題目會使用 同等關係、對等關係和因果關係
They are made with these structures in mind.
它們都是由這些結構生出的
And of the three, which do you think is most important?
在這三種關係間 你們覺得哪個最重要？
Kosugi.
小杉
Equivalence?
同等關係？
That's right. Equivalence.
沒錯，同等關係
That is to say, paraphrasing.
換言之，改述
This is not limited to literature.
這不僅限於語文
English, math, literature, science, and social studies.
英語、數學、語文、理科和社會
You need the ability to paraphrase.
所有科目都需要改述的能力
-All subjects? -Mizuno.
-所有科目？ -水野
For example, math is a subject where we expand a given formula
比如說在數學中 我們需要展開一項公式
and change given phrases into numbers
將題目內文轉換成數字
with equivalence relations.
是一種等價轉換的科目
If you only remember formulas
如果你記得公式
and you can't paraphrase the values, you can't find the answers.
而無法將內文改述為數字 你是解不了題的
In science and social studies, the information is paraphrased
理科和社會則是將 教科書上得到的知識與資訊
from your textbook to match the form of the question.
轉換成符合題目要求形式的回答
Of course, in literature and English,
語文不用說，英文也是
with the power of paraphrasing, you can understand the other.
都是需要使用改述的能力 來理解的科目
Like when you translate to English.
以英文翻譯為例就很好懂吧
Got it, everyone?
明白了嗎，各位？
All subjects require the ability to paraphrase.
所有科目都需要改述的能力
That is to say, for example, in short,
換言之、比如說、簡而言之
so to speak, namely, in other words.
所以說、也就是、換句話說
What is it saying? If you keep asking, you'll find the answer.
它們正在說什麼？ 如果持續追問，你就會找到答案
-That is to say. -For example.
-換言之 -比如說
-In short. -So to speak.
-簡而言之 -所以說
-Namely. -In other words.
-也就是 -換句話說
Alright? Problems posed by UTokyo
聽好了，東大出的題
are mostly "Paraphrase this sentence."
大多都是“改述這句子”
That is to say, if you have reading comprehension,
換言之，如果你們有閱讀理解能力
you can improve your level significantly in all subjects.
你們所有的科目的能力都會明顯提高
The key to passing the UTokyo exam
通過東大入學考的關鍵
is reading comprehension.
就是閱讀理解
Yes, sir!
是！
A trick we can use for all subjects? What a deal!
一個所有科目都能用的技巧？ 真是划算！
Literature has never made so much sense.
語文忽然就變得好懂了
-Even Fujii was taking notes. -Huh?
-就連藤井也在抄筆記 -什麼？
Shut up.
閉嘴
-Fujii, you were taking notes? -Don't look!
-藤井，你抄筆記了？ -別看！
-Show me! -I'll catch the dumb.
-讓我看看嘛！ -你會害我變笨的
I wish you would try for UTokyo with us.
真希望妳會和我們一起進攻東大
Not just the study camp.
而不只是合宿而已
MOM NEW MESSAGE
（媽媽，新消息）
What?
什麼？
- Huh? Does "track" end in "c" or "k"? -It's "k." Nao, you lose.
-最後的字母是“c”還是“k”？ -是“k”，早瀨，妳輸了
-What! -Yay! I can take this off.
-什麼？ -太好了！我終於能脫下這個了
-Ready? -Idiot!
-準備好了嗎？ -笨蛋！
Idiot!
笨蛋！
The UTokyo Special Course is acting weird again.
東大專科又做怪事了
Aren't you embarrassed?
你們不覺得丟臉嗎？
Do we need to walk while we do this?
我們真的需要在外面走動嗎？
Moving your body helps to remember things.
活動身體有助提升記憶力
Ready?
準備好了嗎？
Kosugi is next. What's wrong?
下一位是小杉，妳還好嗎？
Nothing. Uh, was it "k"?
沒事，是“k”嗎？
Um…
呃…
Dad?
爸爸？
I'm head of the UTokyo Study Course. Kenji Sakuragi.
我是東大專科的負責人櫻木建二
What is this about?
這是怎麼回事？
Forcing her to go to university.
強迫她上大學
Is there a problem?
有什麼問題嗎？
My daughter's future is family business.
我女兒將來要打理家族生意
You don't get to decide.
不由你來決定
Of course. Mari herself gets to decide.
當然了，應該由麻里她自己來決定
Mari doesn't want to go to university.
麻里不想上大學
Right? Mari.
對吧，麻里？
How about it? Mari.
怎麼了，麻里？
Well? Speak!
怎麼了？說話啊！
Please calm down.
請冷靜一點
What are you quiet for?
妳幹嘛沉默？
You don't want to go to university, do you?
妳不想上大學，對吧？
Well? Mari.
對吧？麻里
I won't… go to university.
我不會…上大學
There you have it.
你聽見了吧？
You forced her to say that.
那是你逼她說的…
I'm her father. I know Mari best.
我是麻里的父親，我最瞭解她
Who do you think you are? Acting high and mighty.
你們以為自己是誰？在這裡裝高尚
I don't care if you're lawyers,
我不管你們是律師還是誰
you're just using my daughter for your reputation.
你們只是為自己的名譽 利用我的女兒而已
That's not true.
不是的
Mari has the skills to get into UTokyo.
麻里有上東大的能力
-That's why… -Skills?
-所以… -能力？
She's a girl. What skills?
她是個女的，有什麼能力？
Gender doesn't have anything to do with it.
性別和能力沒有關係
Women always get so hysterical like that.
女人總是那樣容易歇斯底里
Anyway, no daughter of mine is going to university.
無論如何，我的女兒是不會上大學的
-I'll withdraw her from school. -Withdraw?
-我要讓她退學 -退學？
I'll withdraw her tomorrow.
我明天就會辦退學手續
Good day.
失陪了
We're going.
走吧
Hey, Mari!
喂，麻里！
Stand up!
快站起來！
-Hey! -Stop!
-喂！ -停手！
Mari!
麻里！
Kenta…
健太…
We're going.
走了
Sir! How can you let Mari go?
老師！你怎麼能放麻里走？
Who does he think he is? Not even asking her opinion.
是啊，他以為自己是誰？ 連她的意見都沒問過
Even though she's so smart…
明明小杉她那麼聰明…
But I think I understand.
我想我能明白
Not being able to go against her dad.
無法違背父親的感覺
Entering UTokyo doesn't need parental permission!
進東大並不需要父母同意！
Yeah, like Fujii said.
對啊，就像藤井說的
If she just takes the test, she can get in.
要是參加考試，她就能入學了
She just needs to make up her mind.
她只是需要下定決心
Mari will go to UTokyo.
麻里會進入東大的
Yeah. She really does want to go.
對啊，她真的很想上東大
Or she wouldn't have come.
否則她就不會來合宿了
But her dad…
但她父親…
Can't we do something?
我們能做些什麼嗎？
Everyone…
大家…
I'll see you tomorrow at 6 a.m.
我們明早六點見
Gather by the Dragon Zakura.
在龍櫻前集合
Wait!
等一下！
Study.
快念書吧
I go away on business and this is what you do?
我不過是出差，妳就搞這些事？
Shoko.
祥子
What were you doing?
妳都在幹嘛？
Poor excuse for a mother.
真是個不稱職的母親
Dad, it's my fault. Just let me graduate.
爸爸，我錯了，請讓我畢業吧
I said no.
我說了不行
You're withdrawing.
妳得從那種學校退學
I'm doing this for your own good.
我這樣做是為了妳好
As if…
這哪是…
What did you just say?
妳剛剛說什麼？
Mari.
麻里
Hey, Mari. Stop!
喂，麻里，給我站住
Mari!
麻里！
What could possibly bring you here?
什麼風把你吹來了？
I come on bended knee.
我是帶著下跪的心情
To ask you a favor.
來請妳幫忙的
STUDY CAMP LAST DAY
（早上八點，合宿最後一天）
Today you're doing this.
今天你們要做這個
"Run, Melos." We already did this.
《跑吧！美樂斯》我們已經做過了
But this time there are keywords.
但這次上面有關鍵字
There are two ways to order the words.
排列關鍵字的方法有兩種
Method one, in chronological order.
方法一，按照時序排列
Arrange them in the order things happened.
根據事件發生的順序排列它們
Hayase, come up here and try it.
早瀨，上來試試看
Yes sir.
是
MELOS, EVIL KING, BELIEVE, FRIEND, HOSTAGE, GIVE UP, PROMISE, COMRADE
（美樂斯、暴君、相信 朋友、人質、放棄、承諾、戰友）
-Like this? -Looks good.
-像這樣嗎？ -不錯
Now, the second method.
接著是第二種方法
The subject predicate method.
主語謂語法
Make sentences saying concretely who did what.
造具體的句子，說明誰做了什麼
-Fujii. -Who, me?
-藤井 -我？
"Melos" made his "friend" a "hostage"
“美樂斯”讓他“朋友”當“人質”
He didn't "give up" on the "promise" and came back.
他沒有“放棄”“約定”回來了
The "evil king" couldn't "believe" it.
“暴君”無法“相信”
He changed his mind and became a "comrade."
他改變了想法，成為他們的“戰友”
Correct.
正確
Make a sample answer using those examples.
大家按照這些重點來寫答案
Model answer: Melos is about to be executed
（標準答案：美樂斯即將被處決）
and appeals to the evil king. He gains a three-day grace period
（他向暴君申訴 透過將朋友塞里努丟斯作為人質）
by taking his friend Selinuntius hostage. Despite the hardships,
（獲得了三天寬限，儘管困難重重）
he does not give up and returns as promised. The king sees their bond
（他仍不放棄，並信守承諾回來了 暴君看見了他們的友誼）
and is moved by their steadfast belief and becomes their comrade.
（並被他們的信念打動 成為了他們的戰友）
I summarized it more clearly.
我的總結更清楚了
So this is a summary.
原來這就是總結啊
A summary is what the author wants to say.
總結是作家想要表達的事情
Reading comprehension is the ability to read what the author wants to say.
閱讀理解能力 則是明白作家用意的能力
It makes sense when you put it that way.
你這麼說，我忽然就明白了
"Believe in your friend and wait."
“相信你的朋友並等待”
That's what the author of "Run, Melos" wanted to say.
這就是 《跑吧！美樂斯》的作者想表達的
-It's so real! -Yeah!
-好真實！ -對啊！
I don't know why, but it's so real!
不知為何，但我覺得很真實！
Mari!
麻里！
Okay, today I have something
好，今天我想要你們
special I want you to do for me.
為我做件特別的事
Pardon me!
不好意思！
Mr. Sakuragi.
櫻木老師
Yes?
是
Hurry up with the withdrawal procedures.
趕快辦好退學手續
Um, about that…
這個，關於那個…
Pardon me.
不好意思
Mr. Kosugi. Before the procedures, could we sit down and talk--
小杉先生，在辦手續之前 我們能不能先坐下來談談…
There's no need. I've already decided.
沒必要，我已經決定好了
Kosugi, is that…
小杉，那是…
You'll withdraw her, then what?
你讓她退學，然後呢？
Of course I'll find her a job immediately.
接著當然會給她找一份工作
And as soon as possible,
然後儘快地
have her marry a good man.
把她嫁給一位好男人
That's true happiness for a woman.
那才是女人真正的幸福
Happiness for a woman?
女人的幸福嗎？
-Mizuno, what do you think? -Uh…
-水野，妳怎麼想？ -這個…
I don't really understand.
我不太明白
-What? -Here's what Mizuno's saying.
-什麼？ -就像水野說的
You don't understand a woman's happiness.
你不明白女人的幸福是什麼
What? So conceited!
什麼？真是自大
Stop treating people like they're idiots!
別再把人當笨蛋了！
I don't care if you graduated from UTokyo!
你是不是東大畢業，我才不在乎
Do you think you're a god?
你以為你是神嗎？
I didn't go to UTokyo. The UTokyo grad is
我沒上東大，這裡的東大畢業生
Mizuno alone.
就只有水野一位
Huh?
什麼？
Well then. See? Mari.
原來是這樣，麻里妳看
Highly educated women
受過高等教育的女人
are cocky and conceited like her.
就和她一樣驕傲又自負
They turn into scum that looks down on you like that!
他們會變成看不起妳的人渣！
That's why women don't need higher education.
這就是為什麼女人不需要受太多教育
Something funny?
很好笑嗎？
You say they don't need higher education.
你說她們不需要受太多教育
But the one who's obsessed with education is you.
但執著於教育的人是你
Huh?
什麼？
Are you obsessed with higher education because you went through a bad experience?
想必是你曾因此受到不甘心的對待吧
Then why don't you give your daughter that same chance?
那你為何不讓女兒有更好的人生？
I told you. Mari doesn't need it.
我說過了，麻里不需要
-Because she's a woman. -Is that why?
-因為她是女人 -真的因為她是女人嗎？
You're wrong.
你錯了
You just don't want your daughter to be in a dominant position over you!
你只是不想讓女兒的地位淩駕於你
No! Don't talk like you know!
才不是！別說得好像你懂似的！
I will talk like I know.
我會像我懂的那樣繼續說
Women don't need higher education?
女人不需要太多教育？
Anachronistic guys like you
像你這種過時的男人
cling to old ways to protect your own pride
堅持以舊時代的方式維護自己的自尊
and don't look at the world!
也不看看現在的世界！
You're free to have a complex. Do what you like.
你可以有情結，你愛怎樣就怎麼樣
But just to protect your pathetic pride,
但為了保護你那可悲的自尊心
you're robbing your daughter of freedom, and trying to force her down!
你正剝奪你女兒的自由 並試著強迫她屈服！
That sort of parent is really trash!
這種家長真是垃圾！
Shut up! Enough of all this.
閉嘴！夠了！
I can't believe you'd speak to a parent that way!
真是無法相信你會這樣對家長說話！
And I can't believe you're standing silently by.
還有你們，竟然安靜地旁觀
My precious daughter going to this school
我珍貴的女兒上這間學校
makes me sick just thinking about it!
想到這我就覺得噁心！
Hey! We're going! C'mon.
喂，走了，快點！
You harm your daughter.
你傷害了你女兒
Can you really say she's your "precious daughter"?
你還能說她是你“珍貴的女兒”？
It doesn't matter the reason.
什麼理由都不重要
There is no reason to commit violence against your family.
這世上沒有對家人使用暴力的理由
Please, just don't sue us!
老師，拜託不要提告！
As a school, we have a responsibility to protect our students.
作為學校，我們有保護學生的義務
We can't overlook violence.
我們不能對暴力視而不見
We must take appropriate action!
我們一定要採取行動！
No…
不會吧…
Or so I thought, and intended to act, but…
我是這麼想的，也想這麼做，但…
Huh?
什麼？
MS. MIZUNO
（水野老師）
Please, don't do that!
拜託了，不要這麼做！
But…
但是…
My father got to be this way
我父親變成這樣
ten years ago when my grandpa died.
是從十年前爺爺去世開始的
The company folded. He went through a lot.
公司倒閉了，他經歷了很多事
He never used to be the violent type.
他以前不是那種會使用暴力的人
One day, I saw him crying alone.
有一天，我看見他獨自哭泣
He seemed so pained.
他看起來很痛苦
So I don't mind waiting.
所以要我忍耐也沒事的
Even though he's like this,
儘管他是這樣的爸爸
he's the only dad I've got.
他也是我唯一的爸爸了
So please don't call the police on him.
所以請你們不要報警抓他
Please.
拜託了
Please!
拜託了！
No matter how stupid or trashy the parent, children trust them
無論家長有多愚蠢，有多垃圾 孩子們都會相信他們
and they have to live with them.
而他們必須承受這些
No matter how weak and naive you are,
無論你有多懦弱、多無知
she remembers when you were her kind father.
她都記得你是她慈祥的父親
No matter how you hurt her,
無論你怎麼傷害她
she keeps believing you'll go back to your old self.
她都始終相信你會變回原來的樣子
That's your daughter.
那就是你的女兒
How long will you keep betraying her?!
你還要背叛她多久？
Sir, stop!
老師，別說了！
A father is the pillar of the family.
父親是一個家庭的支柱
He wants his family to be happy.
他想要一個家庭幸福
He is a big, strong support pillar!
他是一個大而強壯的支柱！
With that worm-eaten, moldy pillar,
以那被蟲蛀爛的、發黴的支柱
how can you support your family?
你要怎麼支撐你最珍貴的家庭？
Is that what you really want?
這真是你想要的嗎？
Shut up! Shut up!
閉嘴！
She understands perfectly.
她很明白
You want to be a good father. You want her to be happy.
你想當個好父親，你想讓她開心
But you couldn't do that.
但你沒辦法
Your irritation! Your suffering!
你的惱怒，你的痛苦！
Let her be free.
讓她自由吧
She, Kosugi, has…
她，小杉…
She has always trusted you.
一直都信任你
Mari…
麻里…
Sir, sir! We did it!
老師，我們做到了！
Kenta! No, not now!
健太，不可以闖進來！
Sorry to disrupt…
不好意思，打擾了…
-Let's go, let's go. -Did you finish?
-走吧 -你們完成了嗎？
Okay, read them here.
好，那在這裡唸給他們聽
Now? I don't think so.
現在？不是吧
In this atmosphere?
在這種氣氛下唸嗎？
You're not confident enough?
你們沒自信嗎？
That's not it. This is my best work!
才不是，這是我最好的作品了
Listen! Mari.
聽好了，麻里
It's not my problem if things go south.
出了差錯可不關我的事
Bring it on.
來吧
"Mari Kosugi should go to UTokyo."
“小杉麻里應該要上東大
"Because she has an amazing ability to focus."
因為她有驚人的專注能力
"For example, people who can focus
比如說，能夠專注的人
can improve the quality of their studying and of their work."
可以提高他們的學習和工作品質
"That is to say, people who can focus on study and work
換言之，可以專注學習和工作的人
are more likely to absorb a lot of knowledge."
更有可能吸收大量知識
"Also, UTokyo is a nexus of knowledge that is useful for society
而且，東大是個樞紐 充滿了有益社會的知識
where people can absorb this knowledge intensively."
人們能在這裡集中地吸取知識
"UTokyo is a place where people who can focus
東大是個讓能專注學習的人
learn to be active in society."
學會在社會中活躍起來的地方
"That is to say, Mari Kosugi
換言之，小杉麻里
should enter UTokyo, and expand her activities."
應該要進入東大 擴充她的活動範圍”
Kosugi, how were their summaries?
小杉，他們總結得怎麼樣？
Say it in front of your father.
在妳父親面前說
I don't know if their sentences were good or not,
我不知道他們的句子造得好不好
but their feelings properly reached me.
但他們想傳達的事，我收到了
Mari, will you go to UTokyo?
麻里，妳會上東大嗎？
I…
我…
I want to try with all of you!
我想和你們一起奮鬥！
I want to go to UTokyo with everyone.
我想和大家一起上東大
Dad…
爸爸…
I'm sorry…
對不起…
I'm sorry.
我對不起你
Please take care of our daughter.
請好好關照我們的女兒
-Yes! -No way, yay!
-太好了！ -不是吧？耶！
-You can go to UTokyo with us? -Yeah!
-妳能和我們一起上東大？ -嗯！
-Alright! Kenta! -Hooray! Hooray!
-太好了！健太！ -太好了！
-That's great, Kosugi! -Kosugi, hooray!
-太好了，小杉！ -小杉，太好了！
-Let's go for it! -Yeah, do it!
-一起加油吧 -嗯，一起加油吧
Hooray!
太好啦！
Whew. Great!
真好
It seems her parents are moving toward divorce as expected.
預料之中，看來她的父母正準備離婚
I found a place for the two of them to live.
我為她們找到了居住的地方
Thank you for everything.
謝謝妳做的一切
Don't misunderstand. This isn't for you.
別誤會了，這不是為了你
I lent you my help to protect my student.
我幫助你是為了保護我的學生
Yes, ma'am.
是
Living under the pressure of a father…
活在父親的壓力之下…
I can understand that.
我能明白那感覺
Where is everyone?
大家呢？
They're cleaning up the cafeteria kitchen.
他們在清理食堂的廚房
Oh.
這樣啊
You have a tough home life too, hey.
妳家也不容易呢
Huh?
什麼？
It's like… complicated?
我的意思是…很複雜？
My two older brothers are super successful.
我兩位哥哥都很成功
Only I messed up my high school entrance exam and was humiliated.
只有我搞砸了高中入學考，被恥笑
I didn't know that.
我都不知道
I guess everyone has something going on.
我想人都有各自的煩惱吧
Nobody has an easy life, do they?
應該大家都不容易吧
Ah, yeah.
嗯，對啊
Man, I'm so tired.
我好累
We're done.
我們做好了
-What were those compositions? -Huh?
-你們剛才寫的是什麼啊？ -什麼？
We've got to re-do the study camp.
我們得再辦合宿了
Bring it on!
放馬過來
But I think I got stronger over these three days.
但我覺得這三天內我變強了
That's a misunderstanding.
那是錯覺
-Sure, sure. -However.
-是啦 -不過
You've got to have more and more misunderstandings.
你們之後要不斷有這種錯覺
Yes, sir.
是
Idiots get overconfident too easily.
笨蛋還真容易得意忘形
-Hm? -What?
-嗯？ -什麼？
Fujii. I'm really glad you came to the study camp.
藤井，我很高興你參加我們的合宿
You stirred up everyone's desire to study.
你激起了大家的學習欲望
-I didn't do… -Thanks for everything.
-我沒… -謝謝你做的一切
Sorry to take up all your valuable time.
佔據了你寶貴的時間，不好意思
-You can go now. -Huh?
-你可以走了 -什麼？
Fujii. Thanks a lot.
藤井，非常感謝
Bye, Fujii. If I think about you working hard, I'll work hard too.
再見了藤井 想到你在努力，我也會努力的
-Bye-bye. -No, hang on!
-拜拜 -不，等一下！
Do you need something?
還有什麼事嗎？
You sure are a pain!
你真是不乾脆！
Can't you be honest with yourself?
你就不能對自己誠實一點嗎？
What the hell?
什麼啊？
I bet you could get into UTokyo.
我想藤井你一定能考進東大
You're already smart.
你本來就很聰明
You stayed behind, studying until late.
你總是留下來學到深夜
And that made me want to stay.
那讓我也想要留下來學習
What'll you do, Fujii?
你要怎麼做，藤井？
You haven't failed the real exam yet.
你還沒在真正的考試輸過
The real battle starts now.
比賽現在才開始
You want to show your brothers and father, right?
你想證明給哥哥們和父親看，對吧？
If you join the Special Course, I'll get you into UTokyo.
要是你加入專科，我會把你送上東大
We start with your personality.
我們會先處理你的性格
I want to get in.
我想要加入
Huh? I can't hear you.
什麼？我聽不見
I want to join the UTokyo Special Course!
我也想加入東大專科！
What should we do, Kenta?
我們該怎麼做呢，健太？
What?
幹什麼？
Fujii, let's study together.
藤井，一起學習吧
I'm sorry about before.
之前的事情，對不起
Sakuragi.
櫻木
Do you think you can get five kids into UTokyo?
你認為自己 能將五位學生送進東大嗎？
We'll have to see.
這個嘛，得看看
I'm counting on you.
無論如何都要做到
To rebuild the school.
為了重建這所學校
You'll take the next UTokyo practice exam.
你們將參加下一輪的東大模擬考試
Wow, that sounds big.
哇，聽起來好厲害
Isn't it still too much for you guys?
對你們來說不會太難了嗎？
You need to keep working on your personality.
你趕快改一改你那個性啦
-It's true. -Listen, everyone.
-對啊 -聽著，大家
If you're not expected to pass this UTokyo practice exam,
這場東大模擬考 被我判定沒有希望錄取的人
you'll be made to quit the course.
我會叫他退出東大專科
-Huh? -What?
-啊？ -什麼？
No!
不是吧！
At this rate, we'll get kicked out!
這樣下去 我們兩個都會被趕出專科！
This is bad! I know it!
這也太糟了！
There will only be three of us left.
東大專科只會剩下我們三個人
To pass, you need a strong heart.
要通過考試，得要有顆強大的心臟
-It's time for you-know-who. -Who?
-是時候請出那人了 -誰？
You don't plan on telling Mr. Sakuragi?
妳沒打算告訴櫻木老師他們嗎？
I have to quit the Special Course, right?
我必須退出東大專科，對吧？
Wasn't making them quit based on results too strict?
依模擬考成績來決定去留 不會太嚴格了嗎？
That's exactly when Hayase will give up.
這就是早瀨會放棄的時候了
They must respect themselves.
他們得肯定自己的能力
If they can do that, they can regain their innate strength.
若能做到這點 他們就能找回原本的實力
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻譯：楊易